It is said that the grass is always greener
كما يقال عشب جاري أكثر اخضرارا دائماً
on the other side of the fence,
من عشبي
and I believe this is true,
وأعتقد أن هذا صحيح
especially when I hear President Obama
خاصة عندما نسمع الرئيس أوباما
often talk about the Korean education system
يتحدث عن نظام التعليم الكوري
as a benchmark of success.
كمقياس للنجاح.
Well, I can tell you that,
حسنا، أستطيع أن أقول لكم أنه
in the rigid structure and highly competitive nature
في بنية صلبة ، وطبيعة ذات قدرة تنافسية عالية
of the Korean school system,
التي تتميز بها نظم المدارس الكورية
also known as pressure cooker,
و التي تعرف أيضاً بطنجرة الضغط
not everyone can do well in that environment.
لا يمكن للجميع أن يبلوا بلاءا حسنا في تلك البيئة.
While many people responded in different ways
و على اعتبار وجود الكثير من ردود الافعال المختلفة
about our education system,
حيال نظامنا التعليمي،
my response to the high-pressure environment
فإن ردي على تلك البيئة ذات الضغط العالي
was making bows with pieces of wood
كان عبر صناعة الأقواس من قطع الخشب
found near my apartment building.
التي أجدها بالقرب من مبنى سكني
Why bows?
لماذا الأقواس؟
I'm not quite sure.
أنا لست متأكداً تماما.
Perhaps, in the face of constant pressure,
ربما، في مواجهة الضغط المستمر،
my caveman instinct of survival
غريزة رجل الكهف للبقاء على قيد الحياة
has connected with the bows.
إرتبطت بالأقواس.
If you think about it,
إن فكرت بذلك
the bow has really helped drive human survival
فالقوس فعلاً قد ساهم في بقاء البشرية
since prehistoric times.
منذ عصور.
The area within three kilometers of my home
المنطقة الواقعة ضمن ثلاثة كيلومترات من بيتي
used to be a mulberry forest
كانت غابة التوت
during the Joseon dynasty,
خلال عهد أسرة جوسون،
where silkworms were fed with mulberry leaves.
حيث تم تغذية دود قز الحرير بأوراق شجر التوت
In order to raise the historical awareness of this fact,
وبغية زيادة الوعي التاريخي لهذه الحقيقة،
the government has planted mulberry trees.
قامت الحكومة بزرع أشجار التوت.
The seeds from these trees
بذور هذه الأشجار
also have spread by birds here and there
دفعت الطيور للانتشار في المنطقة
nearby the soundproof walls of the city expressway
قرب الجدران عازلة للصوت المتوضعة على نواح الطرق السريع في المدينة
that has been built around the 1988 Olympics.
و التي في زمن دورة الألعاب الأولمبية عام 1988.
The area near these walls,
المنطقة القريبة من هذه الجدران،
which nobody bothers to pay attention to,
و التي لا يلتفت إليها أحد
had been left free from major intervention,
تركت بكراً دون أي تدخل يذكر
and this is where I first found my treasures.
وهنا حيث وجدت كنزي الأول
As I fell deeper into bow making,
و شعرت برغبة عميقة تجاه صنع قوس رماية
I began to search far and beyond my neighborhood.
لقد بدأت بالبحث في مناطق أبعد من الحي الذي أقطن فيه
When I went on school field trips,
وعندما كنت أذهب في الرحلات الميدانية المدرسية
family vacations, or simply on my way home
أو خلال الإجازات العائلية، أو ببساطة في طريقي عودتي إلى المنزل
from extracurricular classes,
من الصفوف الاضافية خارج المناهج الدراسية
I wandered around wooded areas
كنت أتجول في جميع أنحاء المناطق المشجرة
and gathered tree branches
و أجمع فروع الأشجار
with the tools that I sneaked inside my school bag.
بواسطة الأدوات المجودة دوماً داخل حقيبتي المدرسية.
And they would be somethings like saws, knives,
مثل المناشير، السكاكين،
sickles and axes
المناجل والفؤوس
that I covered up with a piece of towel.
و التي كنت أغطيها بمنشفة لكي لا يراها أحد
I would bring the branches home,
كنت أجلب الاغصان إلى المنزل
riding buses and subways,
و أشرع بركوب الحافلات ومترو الإنفاق،
barely holding them in my hands.
و بالكاد كنت أستطيع حمل تلك الاغصان
And I did not bring the tools here to Long Beach.
حتماً لم أحضر أياً من أدواتي إلى مؤتمر تيد هنا في لونغ بيتش
Airport security.
بسبب خوفي من أمن المطار.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In the privacy of my room, covered in sawdust,
في غرفتي المليئة بنشارة الخشب
I would saw, trim and polish wood all night long
كنت أقوم بتقليم وتلميع الخشب طوال الليل
until a bow took shape.
حتى أبلور شكل القوس.
One day, I was changing the shape of a bamboo piece
ذات يوم كنت أحاول ضبط شكل غصن من البامبو
and ended up setting the place on fire.
وانتهى بي الأمر إلى إضرام النار في المكان.
Where? The rooftop of my apartment building,
أين ؟ على سطح مبناي
a place where 96 families call home.
المكان الذي يسكنه 96 عائلة
A customer from a department store across from my building
أحد الزبائن من متجر مقابل للمبنى
called 911,
إتصل على 911
and I ran downstairs to tell my mom
فهرعت جرياً إلى الأسفل لكي أخبر أني
with half of my hair burned.
و بنصف شعر محروق
I want to take this opportunity
بالمناسبة أريد أن أنتهز هذه الفرصة
to tell my mom, in the audience today:
لكي أقول لأمي أمام الحضور اليوم:
Mom, I was really sorry,
أمي، أنا آسف حقاً
and I will be more careful with open fire from now on.
وسوف تكون أكثر حذراً من الآن فصاعدا عندما يتعلق الامر باستخدام النار
My mother had to do a lot of explaining,
اضطرت والدتي حينها لسرد الشرح الوفير لما كنت اقوم به
telling people that her son did not commit
لكي تقنع الناس أن ابنها لم يرتكب
a premeditated arson.
إفتعال حريق بصورة متعمدة مع سبق الإصرار.
I also researched extensively on bows around the world.
على منحى آخر أجريت العديد من البحوث على نطاق واسع حول أقواس حول العالم.
In that process, I tried to combine
في تلك العملية، حاولت الجمع بين
the different bows from across time and places
أقواس مختلفة من عبر الزمن والأماكن
to create the most effective bow.
لإنشاء القوس الأكثر فعالية.
I also worked with many different types of wood,
وعملت أيضا مع العديد من أنواع الخشب المختلفة ،
such as maple, yew and mulberry,
مثل القيقب، الطقسوس والتوت،
and did many shooting experiments
وقامت بالعديد من تجارب إطلاق النار
in the wooded area near the urban expressway
في منطقة مشجرة بالقرب من الطريق السريع
that I mentioned before.
التي ذكرتها مسبقاً
The most effective bow for me
القوس الأكثر فعالية بالنسبة لي
would be like this.
هو مثل هذا.
One: Curved tips can maximize the springiness
أولاً : وجود إنحناءات أمثل لمرونة أكبر
when you draw and shoot the arrow.
خاصة حين تحديد الهدف وإطلاق السهم.
Two: Belly is drawn inward for higher draw weight,
ثانياً : منتصف قوس متجه نحو الداخل لعزم أكبر حين شد وتر السهم
which means more power.
مما يعني المزيد من القوة و العزم
Three: Sinew used in the outer layer of the limb
ثالثاً : استخدام وتر في الطبقة الخارجية للقوس
for maximum tension storage.
لتخزين الحد الأقصى من العزم
And four: Horn used to store energy in compression.
رابعاً : وجود طرفي هلال لتخزين عزم أثناء الضغط
After fixing, breaking, redesigning,
بعد التثبيت، و الكسر، و إعادة تصميم،
mending, bending and amending,
و الإصلاح المتكرر ، و الحني والتعديل
my ideal bow began to take shape,
قوسي المثالي بدأ يأخذ شكله،
and when it was finally done,
وعندما إنتهيت منه أخيرا،
it looked like this.
بدا هكذا
I was so proud of myself
أنا فخور جداً لنفسي
for inventing a perfect bow on my own.
لاختراع قوسي المثالي
This is a picture of Korean traditional bows
هذه صورة الأقواس التقليدية الكورية
taken from a museum,
و هي مأخوذة من المتحف
and see how my bow resembles them.
أترون كيف تتشابه تلك الاقواس مع قوسي
Thanks to my ancestors
و اتقدم بالشكر لأجدادي
for robbing me of my invention. (Laughter)
لسرقة اختراعي. (ضحك)
Through bowmaking,
عبر صناعة الأقواس
I came in contact with part of my heritage.
شعرت بالاتصال بجزء من تراث بلادي.
Learning the information that has accumulated over time
إذ تعلمت من المعلومات التي تراكمت على مر الزمن
and reading the message left by my ancestors
وقراءت الرسالة التي خلفتها أجدادي
were better than any consolation therapy
كانت تلك التجربة أفضل من أي العلاج و أي عزاء
or piece of advice any living adults could give me.
أو أي نصيحة يمكن أن يقدمها لي أي من البالغين من حولي
You see, I searched far and wide,
أترون .. لقد بحثت و نظرت بعيداً
but never bothered to look close and near.
لكن لم أكلف نفسي بالنظر و البحث من حولي
From this realization,
من هذا الإدراك،
I began to take interest in Korean history,
بدأت بالاهتمام بالتاريخ الكوري،
which had never inspired me before.
الذي كان مصدر الهام لي من قبل.
In the end, the grass is often greener
في نهاية المطاف على عكس ما قلته في بداية الحديث ، غالباً ما يكون عشبي
on my side of the fence,
أكثر إخضراراً من عشب جاري
although we don't realize it.
على الرغم من أننا لا ندرك ذلك !
Now, I am going to show you how my bow works.
الآن، سوف أريكم كيف يعمل قوسي
And let's see how this one works.
دعونا نرى كيف يعمل هذا
This is a bamboo bow,
هذا هو القوس الخيزران
with 45-pound draw weights.
بعزم رمي 45 باوند
(Noise of shooting arrow)
(صوت إطلاق سهم )
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A bow may function in a simple mechanism,
قد يعمل القوس عبر آليه بسيطة،
but in order to make a good bow,
ولكن من أجل صنع قوس جيد
a great amount of sensitivity is required.
يطلب ذلك الكثير من الدقة و الحساسية
You need to console and communicate
كما أنك بحاجة إلى التواصل و التعامل
with the wood material.
مع المواد الخشبية بحرفية .
Each fiber in the wood
كل ليف من ألياف الخشب
has its own reason and function for being,
له سبب و وظيفة خاصة به
and only through cooperation and harmony among them
وفقط من خلال التعاون والانسجام فيما بينها
comes a great bow.
ويتشكل القوس العظيم
I may be an [odd] student
ربما يعتبرني البعض طالباً غريباً
with unconventional interests,
باهتمامات غير تقليدية،
but I hope I am making a contribution
ولكني أأمل أنني أساهم
by sharing my story with all of you.
بتقاسم قصتي معكم جميعا.
My ideal world is a place
حول فكرتي حول العالم الملائم للحياة
where no one is left behind,
حيث لا يبقى أحد متخلفاً عن الآخر
where everyone is needed exactly where they are,
حيث يكون كل شخص في هذا العالم في مكانه الملائم و المناسب له
like the fibers and the tendons in a bow,
تماماً مثل ألياف وأوتار القوس،
a place where the strong is flexible
مكان يكون في القوي مرن
and the vulnerable is resilient.
و الضعيف رشيق
The bow resembles me,
القوس يمثلني
and I resemble the bow.
و انا امثل القوس
Now, I am shooting a part of myself to you.
الآن، أنا أطلق جزء من نفسي نحوكم
No, better yet, a part of my mind
لا، الأفضل من ذلك، لقد أطلقت جزء من فكري
has just been shot over to your mind.
نحو فكركم
Did it strike you?
هل أصبت الهدف ؟
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)